[Music]
a
hello welcome everybody good day good
evening to all of you and I hope you're
doing great and welcome to the latest
episode of the ASA wiet show the science
Edition so uh this is going to be a
hybrid kind of session I'm going to take
a bunch of questions that you have asked
in the comments maybe 10 15 of those and
then I will take some questions from the
live chat itself so that those of you
whose questions I could not take from
the comments maybe I can answer that on
the live chat and as always let us see
who all is on the live chat and I will
greet some of you I can see Malika
Sachin geopolitical dub hello endan
Banda Panda Karan Bish prna inder Kumar
yadav nikil Malik Sayad hi Omer Omer hi
Matrix uh karik Sharma somia data as
minor hello ashini hi Namaste threat rer
Namaste nikil melodi Sachin giri GK band
rag solanki Shri ramachandra
namaha uh and lots of other people Rahul
G
rajat pragati gopin bisra lost pravina
pnu karik Sharma utar Patel anthon rain
rain sarak capila inder Kumar yadav
Padma Manan Karan Jaga sham kumardas
Yash yadav Shashank
harha Hari hello adity Anand goel rajat
Prat Arya nikil Ren dor hello manindra
Singh Anon rain Dr J Shankar hello
pragati again uh as Nihari hello
sham Sagar hi Aditya and
Priyanka arush sha Vishnu gopinath
pravina Jubal and everybody else ashik
zad Rohan Skywatch Rohan BD Vishnu
mohanan and everybody else okay uh done
with the greetings uh let us go into the
questions and before I begin let me uh I
should do this more often I would like
to thank ramal lakmi spe specifically
for all the work that he does for all of
us every time puts out the time stamps
for every live stream I really really
appreciate that thank you so much ramal
lakmi never met you I don't know who you
are maybe I would like to meet you
someday somewhere but thank you so much
for the work that you do I really
appreciate that that's so helpful for
everybody who watches and it it helps me
too because I don't have to put up that
time stamps myself so ra R LMI G thank
you so much I really appreciate that
okay with that I would like to and put
that in the STS
please okay let's let's take the
questions okay question number one is
cloning does human cloning work if we
clone genius scientists we get a large
will we get a large number of Genius
scientists just by cloning them okay
that's a good question cloning cloning
it's science fiction isn't it I've I
mean I've seen as a kid various science
fiction movies about cloning and stuff
kind of sounds like Dr Frankenstein
stuff cloning so what is cloning and can
humans be cloned and this question that
you asked can you just uh clone 100
Albert Einstein if you have the their
genetic data so how does cloning work
cloning has been done as far as we know
on nonh human animals the first animal
to be cloned was Dolly the sheep I think
in the UK 1996 97 somewhere around that
time I don't remember which year it was
either 96 or 97 the end of the last
century the 20th century
cloning so how was cloning done this is
biology which is not exactly my field
but let me try and explain what it is
because it's interesting so first of all
how does reproduction happen birds and
the bees from a biological perspective
yeah how do do mammals reproduce
so we have somatic cells in our body
which are neither egg nor sperm regular
cells okay apart from the red blood
cells all other cells most other cells
are somatic cells they contain two sets
of chromosomes two sets of chromosomes
and that put together is your DNA your
your blueprint for life
so when reproduction happens you have an
egg that merges or fuses with a
sperm one from the mother's side one
from the Father's Side these are two
different sets of of
chromosomes the egg has one one set of
chromosomes the sperm has one set of
chromosomes they Fus together and then
it creates what's called what a zygote
which has two sets of chromosomes so one
set from the mother one set from the
father from the father and that gives
the the child its own unique set of
genetic characteristics that's how it
happens and then then the zygote will
split into multiple it starts splitting
cell cell division happens and then
eventually it becomes
a um an
and then it eventually after whatever
period of time for humans it's 9 months
other animals is different and then
living being is born that's how it
happens now in cloning what they do is
you take so how was Dolly the sheep
cloned so they take an egg from the
female uh sheep the the mother and the
egg contains a nucleus which has one set
of chromosomes from the mother and what
they do is that using a very thin needle
they take out the nucleus
from the egg so the egg is an empty egg
now it has no no genetic material inside
and then they take a somatic
cell from the animal that you want to
clone and you take out the genetic
material from there you inject that in
you insert that into the egg and then
you induce that to to
multiply cell division should happen and
I think they they keep that so typically
somatic cells are they differentiate
there is differentiation which means
that if you take a cell let's say which
is which is a hair cell okay it gives
rise to hair then it will only produce
more hair cells if you take a skin cell
from from the skin of an animal it will
only if you if it if you make it divide
it will only produce skin cells so even
though it contains the entire genetic
blueprint the entire DNA but it will it
it will only produce that sort of cell
but if you place that under starvation
conditions of or certain specific
conditions then it can divide and and
produce the genetic BL blin for Life
essentially the entire thing so that's
what they do and that that somatic cells
DNA is is placed inside the empty egg
and then it is induced to undergo cell
division and out of I think for for
Dolly the sheep they tried it for more
than 200 almost 300 cells 300 eggs like
that and only one was able to actually
succeed in and give you a
full-term um baby sheep and then after
that they've they've cloned I think
other animals cats dogs horses cows what
not and I I hear that in China or
somewhere they've cloned monkeys and
possibly they may be experimenting with
human beings in China things work
differently but there are ethical
concerns about about cloning especially
when it comes to human beings beings uh
but you see clones in real life when
when you have identical twins or
triplets or quadruplets those are
essentially clones of each other same
more or less the same DNA so those are
clones but you can do it artificially by
various means so it's been more than two
and a half decades since the the first
cloning happened and now many other
animals have been cloned so the same uh
technique the same process can
hypothetically theoretically
theoretically be applied to human beings
as well but obviously uh there are
ethical concerns about this and I think
such research is banned in most
countries but let's say hypothetically
you I think when Albert Einstein died
they removed his brain and I think it's
a it's preserved in various parts in
various universities and hospitals and
what what not for for medical research
so I
suppose but of course that will be
that'll be preserved in form alide so
the cells would have died and all that
but in case you
had viable somatic cells from Albert
Einstein then you could clone that and
you could produce a whole bunch of new
Einstein or you take anybody else any
other
genius uh so that would give you
genetically identical copies of that
person but then it will be born as a
baby and then it'll grow up in its own
way so you may maybe let's say you make
10 of those 10 Einstein let's say or 10
ramanujan or whatever then does it mean
that each of these individuals who is
copy of the original will they all be
Geniuses well there is no guarantee of
that there is no guarantee that that
will happen because there's a lot of uh
you know there there's a debate about
nature versus nurture okay you
are you have the the the potential to be
a genius but it all depends on your
upbringing and the specific
circumstances that you pass through and
maybe see Albert Einstein for example he
was fond of playing the violin and he
had many other interests apart from
physics so maybe one of these uh copies
the Clones may have a different set of
interest and maybe he or she he
obviously want may may not want to
pursue theoretical physics so there is
no guarantee that if you clone somebody
you get the exact same interests and the
exact same life path there are so many
variables at Play that produce a certain
specific set of results so yeah cloning
can work humans can theoretically be
cloned if you can clone other animals
you certainly can clone humans there are
ethical very serious ethical concerns
about this because you're essentially
playing with life and creating
artificial humans or designer babies you
can create and all which uh obviously
could be morally ethically wrong so it
is this sort of research is is banned in
most countries as as far as we
know and even if you were to clone
humans there is no guarantee that if you
clone Albert Einstein maybe you make 10
replicas of Albert Ein it doesn't
there's no guarantee that each of these
replicas will be as interested in
theoretical physics and as much of a
genius as the original they'll have the
same DNA for sure but depending on a
wide variety of other factors and
parameters their lives could turn out
entirely differently and after all it's
a human being with its own agency so he
so the each of these clones it's an
autonomous human being right with full
rights so they have the right to do
whatever they want you can't put them
put you know put them on an assembly
line and ask them to start solving
theoretical physics problems that
doesn't work like that they don't own
those people so yeah that that's a deal
but that's what cloning is about and
definitely humans can be cloned but yeah
there are issues with
that okay next question is by feminist
Slayer and the question is is it
feasible to capture and store the energy
from lightning strikes to fulfill our
energy needs yeah so that's an
interesting question uh capturing and
storing the energy of lightning strikes
uh for to fulfill uh the energy needs of
human beings so there are multiple
challenges when it comes to this and
it's actually if you look at the
challenges it's quite impractical on a
large scale with the kind of technology
that we have today so first of all
lightning strikes are extremely
infrequent you cannot predict where
lightning will strike right so they are
infrequent and they are completely
random completely unpredictable so it's
very difficult to know where lightning
is going to strike where the next
lightning strike will happen and if you
don't know where it's going to strike
then how do you capture that first of
all okay so the first challenge is that
we don't know where lightning is going
to strike next that's the first thing
now there are some areas some parts of
the world where you have more frequent
lightning so the probability of
lightning strike in a particular area
could be could be much higher but you
would have to create extensive
infrastructure and storage systems and
all that to first of all capture the
lightning strike and then store that
energy effectively now uh then there is
the the issue that the energy that is
contained in a single lightning strike
is actually quite small compared to the
actual Global energy demand so a single
lightning strike would have a few
hundred megawatt hours of energy okay
which is a good amount of energy but
it's a fraction of what the global
energy consumption is which is billions
of Mega megawatt hours anually so you
would have to capture I don't know how
many lightning strikes you just do the
math to be able to you know sustain or
or make up for the global demand and uh
then the process let's say you you know
know that the lightning is going to
strike here let's say Okay suppose you
know it the question is how do you
capture it and how do you store it how
do you capture the energy and how do you
store the energy so there are
technological challenges when it comes
to that also because when it comes to
lightning strikes what in what form do
we do do they release their energy so
lightning strikes release their energy
essentially in the form of Light which
is electromagnetic radiation and there
is heat so there is light there is heat
and there are
there is other kinds of electromagnetic
electromagnetic radiation so all of this
the light the Heat and the
electromagnetic radiation would have to
be captured and converted into usable
forms of energy which typically is
either electricity or or chemical
storage chemically stored
energy so and this conversion process of
capturing and converting would probably
involve significant energy losses and
you would need complex and expensive
equipment and infrastructure to do that
so there are so many challenges and the
the payoff is is relatively small so you
can use lightning conductors you know
those lightning rods and all to attract
lightning strikes that you could do and
then you could perhaps store some of
that energy and I'm not sure if
experiments have we done all that but
you would need to actually scale this up
scaling it up so for example if you want
to capture wind energy you can just put
500 large scale uh wind turbines on on a
hill range that way you can capture
significant amount of wi wind energy and
you can reasonably predict how much
energy you will be this will output for
you so that that is reasonably
predictable because you know the weather
patterns and all but when it comes to
lightning strikes it's it's very random
very sporadic very spontaneous very
random and then you can't capture all
that energy so because of this I mean
it's an intriguing concept it's
interesting but it's it's overall
impractical it's overall un unfeasible
you know Rel relatively small amount of
energy that is contained in each
individual lighning strike and the
complete Randomness and unpredictability
and the technological challenges so all
of that makes it uh impractical so more
practical more reliable sources of
renewable energy are solar energy I mean
solar energy is you know how much
sunlight a particular part of the world
receives or your rooftop You can predict
how much sunlight it'll receive over a
year so you can capture that or wind
energy or hydroelectric power for
example if you have a waterfall if if
you got a fast moving River or whatever
if you got a dam then you can do this
reliably and predictably so these
methods are better more practical and
more reliable sources of of uh renewable
energy as compared to trying trying to
capture lightning in a bottle
essentially right so yeah that's that's
what it is so it's not feasible it's not
practical okay herel says how did the
planet Thea collide with the Earth where
the orbits of the solar system unstable
and it can it go unstable in the future
uh during the final days of the sun when
it starts growing bigger due to running
out of hydrogen okay multiple questions
in here but let's talk about the giant
impact hypothesis yeah so about 4 and a
half billion years before today in the
early days of the solar system when the
solar system was in its infancy where
everything was still hot and chaotic uh
the Earth was a rather hellish Place
molten ball of magma which had just
started cooling on the outside and a
crust would have formed and you had lots
of what we call
planetesimals in orbit around the sun
which are like dwarf planet like objects
bodies many very large in number
reasonably large in number you had lots
of these space debris rocks and all
which were impacting the Earth and all
that and the solar system was much more
chaotic than it is right now so it was
still chaotic there was still you know
the orbits had not yet settled of the
various planets and planet dismals and
all that there were collisions I mean we
have an asteroid belt between the orbits
of Mars and Jupiter which probably was
caused by the impact of some two large
objects which scattered the the debris
all over the place so you the as belt
and you had various Planet symbols so it
is believed this is a an a hypothesis
but with reasonably strong evidence that
there was a collision about 4 and a half
billion years ago
roughly between the Earth and a roughly
Mars sized object Planet which is given
the name of
Thea so this uh Thea would probably have
been in one of the lrange points of the
earth maybe L4 or L5 okay you can look
it up what that is what lrange points
are I'll not go into the detail details
right now I must have spoken about that
before so maybe Thea was you know one of
the lrange points of the earth and maybe
it was the the gravity of another planet
maybe Mars maybe Jupiter or whatever
that kind of dislodged this Thea from
its orbit and it ended up colliding with
the Earth but it was not a very strong
headon Collision it was a glancing
collision and what that did is that it
ejected a lot of material from both the
objects Earth as well as Thea into the
orbit of the earth and the two cores of
the two planets of the earth and Thea
merged together much of the stuff was
vaporized and it went into orbit around
the Earth and after a few months or
years it coales into a satellite object
which is now the
moon okay and we have NASA Etc they have
analized rocks from the Moon and there
seems to be evidence that kind of
corroborates this hypothesis this giant
impact
hypothesis so uh that is what is
believed to have happened and this is
the I think the most uh most widely
accepted theory of how the moon came
into existence the Earth's moon so in
the infancy of the solar system about 4
and a half billion years ago yes the
orbits were kind of unstable of all the
planets Planet decimals there could have
been objects that are no longer around
and uh yeah so the so the objects were
the orbits were more unstable now they
have settled down in the past 4 billion
or so years there's not been much too
much of a change in the orbits of the
various planets 8+ 1 nine planets let's
say I still count Pluto as a planet
because as a kid I it I saw it as a
planet so there's not been much change
in the past four billion years now what
about the
future uh H asks about the final days of
the sun when it becomes when it becomes
a red giant so in the in the future
let's say about five billion years from
now roughly the sun will be a red giant
because it's going to it's going to
undergo a whole process which which uh
which turns it into a red giant its
outer layers will expand expand expand
and when that happens the outer layers
of the sun will engulf the orbit of the
earth which means the Earth will be
inside the
Sun so it doesn't matter then right how
does it matter what the orbits are going
to be like our planet will be swallowed
up by the parent
star so yeah in the future there could
be some more perturbations Etc of the
orbits to some extent but more or less
they'll remain stable there is some
possibility that Venus may be kicked out
of its or in the future maybe a couple
of two three billion years from now that
could happen because of various orbital
uh uh calculations Etc it could happen
but for now for the foreseeable future
as far as we humans are concerned
there's going to be no change as far as
we are concerned look how old are we
humans as a species half a million years
400,000 years yes in another 400,000
years from now in the future nothing's
going to change as far as the orbits of
the planets are concerned so we are
about that much old and if we go back go
into the future that much 400,000 years
half a million years hopefully we still
exist as a species well you won't see
much change everything will still remain
the same and look the same it's only
when you talk about billions of years
that you will have changes and that
really is nothing is not something we
should be concerned about because that's
way too far in the future from the
perspective of a single human lifetime
or
even you know
human Collective memory uh and yeah when
the sun becomes a red giant the Earth
will become part of the sun it will be
engulfed by the Sun so orbits don't
really matter at that point in time
anymore
okay Rohan BD says light travels faster
than any other particle or wave since it
does not interact with the higs field
that is correct yes but space itself
expands faster than light I assume that
means that space also does not interact
with the higs
field if neither light nor
space is interacting with the higs field
B field then why can't light travel as
fast as uh as space
expands okay so what is the higs field
the higs field is the field the the the
quantum field of the higs B
on and it is the interactions of the
various fundamental particles with the
higs field are what uh endow these
particles with mass so when it comes to
some particles they interact strongly
with the higs field so they have they
are more massive and some particles
interact very uh very not strongly
weakly with the higs field which is why
they have less mass and some particles
don't interact with the Hig field at all
which is why they are massless so our
friends the photons the light particles
okay uh they do not interact with the
higs field and this is why this travel
at the maximum maximum speed allowed in
the universe the speed limit of the
universe maximum speed is roughly
300,000 m/ second that's the speed of
light in vacuum so that is the speed the
maximum speed at which uh you can go in
the universe and photons travel at that
speed because the higs field because
they don't interact with the Hig field
now the expansion of space we're talking
about is a whole different phenomenon
okay it is described by the metric
expansion of space which is governed by
the equations of general relativity and
space can expand at any rate and during
during certain uh periods of the
universe's history especially during the
very very beginning of the universe's
history just after the big bang when you
had inflationary the inflationary period
space actually expanded much faster than
the speed of light and this expansion of
space itself is not limited by the speed
of light because it is not the movement
of objects through space it is the
expansion of space
itself so there's a speed limit on the
movement of objects through space time
through space let's not let's not call
it space time right now let's just say
space three dimensional space so when it
comes to the movement of objects and
particles through space there is a speed
limit
300,000 meters per second roughly
but the expansion of space itself there
is no speed limit there okay so uh so
that's the deal so the expansion of
space is a different kind of phenomenon
it's not particles moving through space
it's space itself stretching the fabric
of space itself stretching and the
expansion of space is not constrained by
the same rules that limit the speed of
particles through space so it can exped
exceed the speed of light without
violating any physical laws so we the
very the famous analogy right the
balloon analogy you take a balloon take
a balloon and you you inflate it so
let's say you have a balloon that is
inflated and it's this large and there's
an ant walking on the surface of the
balloon okay so the surface of the
balloon which you are inflating it
represents space and the Ant that is
walking on the surface of the balloon it
is a particle and the Ant is a massive
particle so it it has a certain speed
limit at which it can walk now you blow
more air into the balloon and then the
ant which is on top of the balloon will
start moving faster away because the
balloon itself is expanding even though
the ant is just let's say it's just
sitting there it is still moving away
from
you and then it may be able to move
faster than any ant can ever move
because you're expanding it at a certain
speed the balloon so that's the kind of
analogy it is okay so the bugs the the
ant is analogous to particles and if you
have a small ant you can say it's a
photon so because the fabric of the the
balloon itself is expanding it can
expand at any rate it can expand faster
than any ant can travel and it doesn't
break the speed of the speed limit of
ants similarly space space itself can
expand at any speed but that doesn't
break any laws of
physics so it's different
phenomena okay it's it's totally
different
phenomena uh yeah so that is the answer
my
friends Vishal Kumar says what are super
critical fluids and why are they
important for us super critical flu
fluids so there is something called you
know substances have uh phases there's
the gaseous phase that's the liquid
phase there the solid phase there is
something in in thermodynamics there is
something called the triple point there
is something called the critical point
it's a drop
so uh let's put this on the screen
should we critical point triple
point critical
point okay let me put that on the screen
a Google Google image
search okay here we are so critical
point in thermodynamics you have a
triple point you have a critical
critical point so the critical point is
the the it's about temperature and
pressure so see any gas exists at a
certain temperature and a certain
pressure the gas that we have around
ourselves the atmosphere the the
atmospheric gas around us it also is it
exists at a certain temperature and
pressure the average temperature around
the world average is about 25° celus and
the average atmospheric pressure is at
sea level is about 1
atmosphere so that is the temp the the
temperature and pressure conditions of
the atmosphere on average at C Level 25°
and one atmospheric pressure now you
have you can
have gases in a container at various
temperatures and pressures so there is a
certain part of this curve where the
temperature and pressure are such that
your gas will reach a critical point
where it is where it will start
exhibiting properties of of of gas as
well as a liquid so it has the
properties so that's where you your your
uh gas or fluid goes Super critical and
it exhibits properties of gases as well
as
fluids and that is is it gives it
certain properties you would otherwise
not find and certain gases uh are used
in industrial processes when you make
them super critical so for example I
think carbon dioxide is carbon dioxide
is one of the most uh commonly used
gases which is made super critical and
it is it has lots of industrial and
other applications food processing
applications
Etc uh so I think when it comes to
carbon dioxide it at about 30 32 or
something degrees Celsius and a pressure
of about 30 or so bar or 80 bar I don't
remember what it is you can look it
up it be it goes Super critical and when
it is super critical it it uh it has
certain uses like uh if you want to
decaffeinate you know remove caffeine
from coffee that can be done you and it
has various other in uh applications I
don't remember all the applications
right now but the deal with super
critical fluids is that they at a
certain temperature and pressure they
start exhibiting properties of a fluid
as well as a gas at the same time and
that can be utilized for all kinds of
industrial and other applications food
processing and so on that's what it
is okay Rohan asks what makes water the
universal solvent why don't other
liquids such as oils Mercury condensed
gases Etc dissolve as many things as
water yes water is a wonderful fluid
water is the source of life we are alive
because of water right and water is kind
of a universal solvent so it has certain
properties that many most other fluid
fluids don't have which makes H2O an
excellent medium for dissolving a wide
range of substances Etc so first of all
there is something called polarity water
molecules are polar what does it mean it
means see we know that water is H2O
there are two hydrogen atoms and and one
oxygen atom in a water molecule so if
you look at a water molecule the
hydrogen atoms have a slightly positive
charge and the oxygen at is a slightly
negative charge which means there is a
polarity okay slight positive charge on
the hydrogen atoms and slight negative
charge on the oxygen atom so this
polarity allows the water molecules to
interact with what's called ionic
compounds and polar compounds through
the formation of hydrogen bonds and uh
hydrogen bonds and ion ion dipole
interactions so that that is one factor
that makes water a great Sol solent and
then like I said there are hydrogen
bonds uh so these water molecules then
they can form hydrogen boms bonds bonds
with other water molecules and many
other substances that also have hydrogen
atoms and lone pairs of electrons these
hydrogen bonds they facilitate the
dissolution process of various
substances they allow other substances
to break up break up out break about the
molecules and they surround these
molecules with water
molecules so hydrogen bonding polarity
and high electric permitivity so water
has a very high reasonably High di
electric constant or or electric per
electrical permitivity which allows it
to separate ions and uh it allows ionic
compounds to dissociate and dissolve in
water that's why salts Etc and other
ionic compounds are are they dissolve
very rapidly very readily in water so
these are the things these are the
properties that make water a great solv
and other liquids like oils like you're
saying oils Mercury condensed gases they
don't have the same combination of
properties so polarity most oils I
believe are not they are non-polar so
they cannot form hydrogen bonds Mercury
is a liquid metal okay so it doesn't
have polarity or hydrogen bonding
capabilities of water and condensed
gases have they also are non-polar and
so on so most of these other liquids do
not have this combination of properties
that that water has and that's why water
is a great solvent in these other
liquids are not so some liquids can
dissolve some specific types of
substances but water is kind of you know
it it is able to dissolve a very wide
range of substances and that is why
water is way better than other liquids
in being a solvent that's why we call it
a call it a universal solvent
ramaki ramal lakmi
says recently I was looking at a video
talking about research about
neurobiology of gender identity and
sexual orientation and that in that he
showed multiple ongoing researches and
talks about how gender is different from
sex as gender is a neurological
phenomenon only in the brain whereas uh
Sex Is Fundamental to the physical
aspects my
thoughts yeah was a good question right
there right gender versus sex okay look
uh I am a very simple person okay I like
to keep things very simple XX versus XY
that's how I see gender and sex okay
very
straightforward and uh look you do an
archaeological dig somewhere you go to
Egypt you go to moeno you go to rakari
whatever place in the world you do an
archaeological dig and you come up
across ancient skeletons of human beings
um what are you going to see you you're
going to see you will want to identify
whether the skeleton is that of a male
or a female right and there are certain
very stand standard straightforward uh
parameters that you look at the width of
the pelvis the hipbone and I think the
the width of the skull I
mean when a human being has more
testosterone the skull Etc is wider and
when it comes to
estrogen or the female hormones Etc that
the pelvis is wider so there are certain
characteristics and the bones are
thicker and heavier in males and all
that so when you're an archaeologist
it's it's very straightforward to
determine whether the individual that
you have discovered buried wherever is a
male or a female okay what that person
identified as it is kind of
irrelevant and from a pure biological
perspective male is a a male individual
is an individual who has two who has One
X chromosome and one one Y chromosome
and females have two X chromosomes it's
as as simple as that now we know that
there are some people some individuals
who genuinely identify as some some
other
gender it's been known throughout
history so a certain small percentage of
the population is going to have a
different uh identity and maybe sexual
orientation right
homosexuality maybe 1 2% I don't know
what the percentage is okay I don't know
in the US these days it's about about
38% or 72% of theom people are
identifies as homosexuals I don't know
what it is but yeah these days it's it's
the trend is increasing almost everybody
wants to jump on the bandwagon and
become a homosexual and lots of people
say that I don't know what gender
identity they have there are so many
different genders these days apparently
so uh look from a biological perspective
it's very straightforward it's either XX
or XY chromosomes and that that's it
okay and there are some very rare cases
of intersex which I'm not very
conversent with what that is so I'll not
talk about that because I not very sure
what that is but there is something
called intersex which has a chromosomal
aspect
apparently uh so neurobiology of gender
identity I don't know it's all whole new
field of research that only exists in
the United States I believe as far as I
know and in the western world and soon
will arrive in other countries wherever
there is Western
influence so uh look I at the end of the
day from my perspective you are free to
live your life as you wish in a free
country like whatever hopefully you live
in a free
country and uh you can identify as
whatever you want you can identify as a
male as a female as something in between
you can identify as a butterfly if you
want as a it's up to you uh and yeah
yeah so that's that's how I see it from
my perspective it's very straightforward
biological gender sex whatever it's just
two Sexes uh but neurologically and from
your that thing you can identify as
whatever you want if it makes you happy
please please identifies as whatever it
is today you can identify as this
tomorrow identifies that entirely your
choice as long as it makes you happy go
do whatever you
like okay swapnil says what is morphic
resonance or morphogenetic field how
applicable is it in understanding nature
and entropy there was a guy called rert
sheld he was a biologist he came up with
with
morpo morphogenetic field or morphic
resonance this is a hypothesis for which
there is no real uh
evidence and it kind of is well
classified probably as pseudo cyes so
what's the basic idea the basic idea
behind morphic resonance morphogenetic
field is that the collective memories of
a species let's say we are the human
species or let's say the species of kis
lupus the wolf or panthera Leo lime
whatever you have a species the
collective memories of a species can
influence the behavior and development
of future members of the species across
time and space through kind of a field
inheritable memory field or resonance
field that is the hypothesis that rert
sheld break put forth I think in the
20th century if I'm not forgot if I'm
not
mistaken but have we observed this field
this memory field or resonance field
obviously we have not observed it okay
um and there is some research about of
the the possibility that uh your DNA
could encode certain inherited
memories uh so that is an ongoing field
of research there seems to be some
evidence that it could be so but that
has nothing to do with with this
hypothesis of Rupert shelrick of this
morphogenetic field so that's what it is
it's a some kind of field non-material
field that transcends space and time so
when you're talking about a non-material
non-physical field you're no longer
talking about science because science
and physics is all about
observable objects physical objects and
observable measurable quantities and
phenomena and when you have a
non-material non-physical field you're
no longer talking about science you're
talking about philosophy or spirituality
something and what's the what's what's
its application to entropy well a
non-material non-physical field how do
you apply that to entropy second law of
Thermodynamics and so on uh I don't
really know so uh this is a hypothesis
not even a theory that doesn't really
have any uh evidence to support it so
yeah the the conventional explanations
are based on genetics and evolution the
the laws of physics and chemistry and
biology which OBS which explain the the
patterns and whatever forms You observe
biologically in nature that's how we do
it because that's something we can
observe we can measure we can track um
and obviously if you have theories based
on that you can either prove them or
falsify them when it comes to these
non-material fields and all you can't
fsy ify them you can prove you can
disprove and you can observe you can
measure you can quantify you cannot do
any of that so that's why it
is well not really science okay so yeah
that's that's morphic resonance
morphogenetic field uh a hypothesis not
really a theory by rert
sheldrick copile says what's your take
on Deja Vu why does that happen I have
two theories we are living same life Etc
again again so sometimes remember okay
you're talking about rebirth okay that's
one
Theory uh and secondly we experience
some future events in our dreams but you
know we don't remember 99% of what we
have dreamed so it could be the reason
for Deja Vu okay all right thank you so
much so what is deja vu deja vu is this
it's a
rather common phenomenon right lots of
people experience theja Vu lots of
people experience they you and they they
they experience something and they get
the feeling they've already seen this
before so let's say you you are walking
you wake up in the morning you go for a
walk and you see something maybe a cat
talking to to a crow a cat and a crow
having a conversation you like oh my God
I've seen this before I've seen this
it's happened before why am I seeing
seeing it again so that's the kind of
thing it is or or whatever experience so
that is deja view now why does it happen
first of all do we I think it's I think
it's a reasonably common phenomenon I
personally have never experienced theu
oh my God I've seen this before it's
never happened to me okay but I may be
perhaps an outlier maybe I may be in a
minority lots of people claim that some
people say that it happens to them all
the time they oh my God I've seen this
before and okay good but uh so how could
we explain this first of all it's it's
it's an
experiential phenomenon it's something
you experience
but you can't measure you can't quantify
it it's it's a psychological
neurological kind of
thing and why does it happen so maybe
it's something to do with the way brain
the brain processes information the Mind
processes information maybe there are
different Pathways to
memory so uh when you see something
maybe the memory of that is stored
through multiple paths and maybe one
path forms faster One path takes longer
to form so you feel like it's happening
twice oh my God I've seen this before
that maybe that is it okay or maybe
something else I'm not really sure what
it is but Deja as far as we know there
is no scientific explanation for that
and the reason is very simple we don't
quite know how the mind works we don't
quite know how the brain works we don't
know quite know how memories
form memories form through a multiple
multitude of Senses we have five senses
touch uh hearing seeing taste and
whatever else it is right and all of
that combined and smell of course so all
of that the combination of all these
it's what forms a memory and there are
it's a very complicated process so many
different nerves and pathways are
involved in that and we don't quite know
how memories are stored in the brain in
the
mind
so when it comes to the brain it's the
least understood organ when it comes to
the mind it's even less understood how
the mind works and where Consciousness
emerges from and how we experience
things uh there is neurology there is uh
Psychiatry Etc Psychiatry is all all
hand waving and
Voodoo okay because the the organ that
you study in Psychiatry you never really
map it measure it and and so on so my
point is we don't quite know how this
happens I know that lots of people
experience theja VI but what is the
mechanism I don't think any psychiatrist
psychologist neurologist will be able to
give you a proper answer an ambiguous
answer all they can say that there are
lots of different possibilities as to
how this happens but they cannot tell
you pinpoint how it specifically happens
it's because we don't understand the
mind we don't understand the
brain we know very little about the
brain so yeah the answer is we really
don't know how this happens but yeah it
does seem to happen to lot to a lot of
people okay yaja says what are naked
singularities do they exist if time
reversal symmetry T symmetry is true in
the theory of general relativity and
naked singularities exist can a naked
Singularity spit out literally anything
like a car a planet a dinosaur a Galaxy
whatever since it can gobble up anything
too if that happens would that mean that
the universe is fundamentally
indeterministic even in general
relativity since we know that the naked
singular since we don't know what the
naked Singularity would spit out okay
what's a singularity and what's a naked
Singularity we're talking about scary
scary objects in the universe okay the
universe is full of mysterious objects
everything is mysterious but
singularities are some of the scariest
and one most dangerous and most
mysterious things in the universe we
have never seen a singularity by the way
uh we know object we have seen object
that hide singularities apparently
within them according to general
relativity and these objects are what we
call black holes and we know we have
observed what seems to be black holes
what most likely are black holes so a
black hole is a region of SpaceTime that
hides what general relativity says is a
singularity and it hides The Singularity
behind a curtain a membrane called an
event horizon and in a black hole The
Event Horizon is the point of no return
once you reach there The Event Horizon
you can never go back outside even light
cannot come out of of the Event Horizon
okay and inside there at the heart at
the core of of this object is a
singularity a singularity is a point in
SpaceTime where the curvature of space
time becomes Infinity the density mass
energy density also becomes
infinity and that is essentially
division by zero which tells you that
there's something wrong with some
something wrong with the equations of
general relativity the Einstein field
equations but let's say that a black
hole has a singularity at its heart but
that Singularity is hidden behind any
event horizon we can't look inside we
simply can't so there is something
called The Cosmic sensorship hypothesis
which says that singularities can only
exist if they are hidden behind an event
horizon a naked Singularity cannot exist
that's a hypothesis called The Cosmic
sensorship hypothesis now certain
Solutions of the field equations
Einstein field equations have naked
singularities which are not hidden
behind in Event Horizon but that's never
been
observed okay so that is what a
singularity is and that's what a naked
singularities as opposed to a black hole
which has an event horizon and a
singularity inside that a hidden
Singularity so you have hidden
singularities you have naked
singularities now what is T symmetry
time reversal symmetry
watch uh let's say you have a tennis
ball where's my tennis ball I don't have
it here you have a tennis ball and you
drop it it bounces b boom boom like that
you take a film of that and then you
reverse the film you play it in the
opposite
direction okay time reversed film so
then you will see that the ball is
bouncing higher and higher but even if
you play the film backwards you will see
that the motion of the ball the bouncing
motion it still obeys the laws of
physics So In classical mechanics in
Newtonian physics you have equations
that involve time T small T if you
replace the small T by minus t which
means you reverse time the equation
still hold perfectly well and that's t-
symmetry time that that's is how you can
think of what T symmetry is time
reversal
symmetry but T symmetry isn't always
observed in the universe for for example
you have the second law of
Thermodynamics which says that one of
the ways to understand to think of the
second law of Thermodynamics is that it
says that
heat flows from always flows from a
hotter object or a hotter part of an
object to a colder part of the object it
never flows from a colder region of the
object to a hotter region of the
object heat always flows from hotter to
colder so there there is no
reversibility if you you reverse time in
that process you will not see heat
flowing from the cold part of the object
to the hot part of the object so there t
symmetry breaks down all right and there
are other cases in which the T symmetry
breaks down the weak nuclear force the
expansion of the universe how do you
reverse that so there are so the
universe doesn't entirely you know T
symmetry doesn't always entirely
hold now if T symmetry is true in the
case of General
relativity and let's say naked
singularities exist then doesn't mean
that they can spit out anything so think
off it this way you're taking a film
let's say a naked Singularity is sitting
there okay sitting there or sitting here
and I'm taking a film of that a video
and some things go inside that all my
books are going are being sucked into it
one by one okay all these books sitting
here this little rhinos sitting there he
also gets sucked in and these other
animals little Indian animals sitting
there they also get sucked in one by one
so I'm taking I'm filming everything I'm
taking a video of all all of that then I
play the video In
Reverse so if T symmetry holds then
essentially it means that you playing
the video in
reverse then what you will what will you
see you'll see the singularity spitting
out exactly what went inside it once
start spitting out dinosaurs and house
plants and planets and galaxies it will
only spit out what went went inside in
the
past so that does not violate
determinism okay so if t- symmetry holds
in general relativity and naked
singularities exist then they will only
spit out what went into them in the past
they won't spit out any random object
planets and dinosaurs and pythons and
fish bows galaxies no no it doesn't work
like that all
right right so it doesn't violate
determinism it will still remain
very entirely
deterministic okay feminist Slayer says
how were gravitons mediator particles
like bons photons and other Elementary
particles generated in the early
universe and what are the details of
their structures
okay so grav first of all let's talk
about gravitons gravitons are
hypothetical bosons hypothetical
particles massless particles spin zero
particles but entirely hypothetical now
gravitons are proposed in various
theories that attempt to merge quantum
mechanics with general
relativity so you have theories like uh
string theory and so on in which you
have this particle which which give you
this particle called the graviton it's a
hypothetical particle it has not been
experimentally observed yet okay
but uh if it exists it's a massless spin
two particle it is angular momentum to
so that's what a graviton is it's a
hypothetical boson a a
mediator uh a mediator particle it
mediates the force of gravity just like
the photon which is a massless spin one
particle is the mediator of the
electromagnetic force similarly the
graviton could be the mediator of the
gravitational force if these theories
are correct okay so that's what a
graviton is that's what uh bosons are
all these Force carriers mediator
particles the w and z boson the the
eight gluons the photon the
hypothetical uh graviton and obviously
the higs boson higs particle these are
bons uh they have integer values of spin
angular momentum fion have fractional
spin 1/2 two thirs Etc minus half and so
on uh so now the question is how were
these Elementary particles generated in
the early universe and when we talk
about the early Universe we're talking
about the very very very initial
instance after the big bang the Big Bang
was not an explosion it was an expansion
of
SpaceTime so in the very moments after
the big bang before the inflationary
Epoch in the universe It is believed
that uh all see we observe four forces
in the universe we have the
electromagnetic force because of which
we have
light then we have gravitation which we
don't understand we don't understand
very well then we have the strong
nuclear force and the weak nuclear force
so there are four forces that we are
aware of it is believed that in the very
very initial instance after the big bang
all of these four forces that are
separate forces today they actually were
all combined into a single they were all
unified into a single Force which is
which we call the ground unified for
force of grand un whatever you want to
call it the grand unified force in the
very initial instance of the after the
big bang and eventually as the universe
expanded rapidly and cooled all the four
forces split out of this Grand unified
Force at various points in time at
various
temperatures symmetry breaking and all
you can look that up so that's what
happened so the forces split up and also
it is it's also believed that in the
very initial instance of the after the
big bang when the four forces were
unified into a single Force at that time
all the elementary particles also
existed in this primordial soup this
Quark gluon
plasma so all these Elementary particles
were all present and then as the
universe expanded and cooled these
various forces these various Elementary
particles froze out of this primordial
soup at different
temperatures so that is what is believed
to have happened so all these Elementary
particles were part of that
extraordinarily dense and hot Quark
gluon plasma that existed in the very
very early instants of the existence of
our universe what are the details of the
structures look uh when it comes to uh
the photon yeah light light particle the
Quantum of light well the photon is is
believe to be a point particle massless
Point particle no structure it has a
wavelength sure yeah well it has a
wavelength but it's it's thought of as a
massless point
particle um the
gluons are also massless Point particles
they they have eight different there are
eight different kinds of gluons with
different color charges color charges
Quantum chromodynamics there's a few
book one or two books over here Quantum
chromodynamics so that's all about color
charges that's the
gluons um the graviton the hypothetical
graviton has an angular momentum of two
and it is massless which would say which
would mean that it's a point particle
the w and z bosons are massive particles
the W boson has what spin half spin
minus no sorry spin minus one spin plus
one I think and what is the the mass 80
or so G or something if I'm not mistaken
okay I don't remember right now roughly
80 GV or something is the mass of the W
boson the Z boson may have a higher Mass
and so on yeah so these particles are
massive particles which means that they
have some kind of internal structure
what structure is there we don't know we
still haven't been able to penetrate
deep inside and actually see what
structure is there but there is mass the
are these are massive particles which
means there is some structure but we
don't quite know what the structure is
we need bigger colliders we need a super
LHC now to maybe investigate that we
have the large hyron collider we need a
super large hyron collider now maybe we
should fund that
maybe maybe that should be funded so
yeah we don't know the the structure of
the W andz bosons but there is some kind
of structure and then there's the higs
boson which is what 125 gev if I'm not
mistaken G by C squ when I say gev it
means gig electron walls divided by the
speed of light
squared okay that you generally say gev
you don't say the C divided by C squ
part so the Hig boson has a mass of
roughly 125 G divided by C squ and if
you do the math and all the units then
you see it's a unit of mass you can
convert that into kilograms if you
like um and it also the higs boson also
since it's massive it would have some
kind of internal structure which once
again we don't know we have just about
discovered the thing we don't quite know
what it looks like and so on so yeah
that's kind of the
answer and
uh yeah so some some of these B have
have structure some don't
don't yaj nalka says the schat strill
solution describing a schat strill black
hole is said to be a vacuum solution in
general relativity does that mean that
the SWAT shill black hole and its inside
are actually vacuum how does a Schartz
chill black hole have a nonzero mass
then okay schill black hole so what's
first of hole what's a Schwartz black
hole a Schwartz black hole is a black
hole that is a rotating black hole in a
non-charged black hole so there are
thing black holes are described by
essentially just three parameters Mass
charge angular momentum mass is how much
mass obviously a black hole has let's
say in kilograms or you could say G me
PV TV whatever electron volts divided by
C squ uh so that's mass then charge
black holes can be charged or uncharged
and then black holes can be spinning or
non-spinning rotating or non non-
rotating Mass charge angular momentum so
that's all you need to know about a
black hole to describe the black hole
fully as far as our understanding of
black holes goes so a schwat shed black
hole is a black hole that has mass but
no charge and no spin it's not spinning
it's just sitting there okay it's a
essentially a spherical Black Hole uh
spinning rotating black holes are kind
of squashed they squashed shape and all
so on so forth okay and so awat Shield
black hole has no charge no no angular
momentum just Mass so now you're talking
about a vacuum solution so the term
vacuum Sol solution in ter in the
context of schwat Shield of the schwat
solution of the Einstein field equations
does not mean that the interior of the
black hole is a vacuum it actually
refers to
U it it is a solution to Einstein's
field equations of general relativity in
the absence of any matter or energy
except for the gravitational field
itself so there is nothing around the
black hole there is no matter there's no
energy there's only the gravitational
field and the Schwartz field solution
describes the curved SpaceTime geometry
outside a spherically symmetric
non-rotating
non-charged Mass distribution okay and
it does not provide any information
about what's inside the black hole apart
from the fact that there is a
singularity at the very center where the
laws of general relativity break down so
that is the short Shield Solution that's
a short Shield black hole so the nonzero
mass of your schat Shield black hole it
arises from the boundary conditions that
are used to obtain the schart shield
solution and it's it's essentially uh
obtained by requiring this the geometry
of the SpaceTime far away from the mass
distribution reduces to the flat
minkovski SpaceTime of special
relativity and so on so U so when you
talk about a vacuum solution it doesn't
mean that there's nothing inside okay
that's not what it is
uh and it doesn't talk about the nature
of the mass distribution itself so there
is a mass in there okay the mass m and
that is that that uh characterizes the
strength of the gravitational field when
it comes to the schwat shield solution
and so on so it doesn't mean that there
is a vacuum inside and obviously it's
not a non-zero Mass it is a non-zero
Mass it is not a zero Mass solution all
right so that's what you mean by a
vacuum solution
okay okay another question so yaja seems
to be a fan of general
relativity the question is the gravity
of a whiteold should be attractive since
it has a positive mass and anti-gravity
has not been found yes the gravity of a
white hole should be attractive correct
but we cannot enter a white hole from
the outside in the same way that we
cannot leave from the inside of a black
hole correct can you resolve this
Paradox would the existence of white
white holes then lead to the breakdown
of causality and lead to an acausal
Universe finally is our universe a white
hole inside which we
reside so yes white holes are
intriguing objects they do raise some
interesting paradoxes and questions
about causality and the nature of the
universe Etc so uh the the Paradox when
it comes the Paradox that you referring
to it it arises from our classical
understanding of gravity and the
assumptions that we made made about the
that we make about the behavior of
SpaceTime near singularities so what is
a white hole what's a white hole
solution in general relativity white
hole is a hypothetical region of
SpaceTime okay that cannot be accessed
from the outside so it's the opposite of
a black hole so when it comes to a black
hole when it comes to a black hole we
cannot access the interior of the black
hole from outside that's because the
event there's a Event Horizon which acts
as a One Way oneway
boundary so you are outside a black hole
and you are going towards the Event
Horizon you can go back go back but once
you are at the event once you cross it
once you cross the threshold it's now
you can there's no way you can return
it's a
oneway uh it's a oneway barrier oneway
membrane so that's a black hole and the
white hole is the opposite of that so
when it comes to a white hole there is
no way you can even reach the Event
Horizon and if you reach that you simply
can't go inside so a white hole is like
a Time reversed black hole so matter and
radiation escapes it is emitted from a
white hole but nothing ever goes inside
it okay so it looks like something that
is a causal there is no causality I mean
how do you know what is causing whatever
is being emitted out of a white hole
where is it coming from what is causing
that right so we we don't know if white
holes exist they may exist but we have
never really observed something that
could be a white hole it is possible
that what we think is a black hole at
the center of a Galaxy could actually be
a white hole there are many active
Galactic nuclei okay which are extremely
energetic and they emit all kinds of
radiation and other substances Jets and
beams and so on lots of light lots of
radiation beams of of material of high
energy particles velocity some of those
could actually be white holes who knows
we don't know and there can be tests
that we can devise that could actually
give us some indication of whether it's
an it's a black hole or it's a white
hole but it's possible that some of
these objects could actually be white
holes now it's important to understand
this that our understanding of physics
it breaks down at the singularities
associated with black holes and white
holes so we need a theory of quantum
gravity which we don't have and this
Theory would Recon general relativity
with Quantum Magics to actually fully
understand the behavior of SpaceTime in
these extreme
conditions so uh one possibility so the
the point about causality that you're
making is is very valid a white hole is
spewing out matter and radiation but
where is that coming from what is
causing it we have absolutely no idea it
actually could be because we don't
understand the physics at these in these
extreme conditions we need a quantum
theory of gravity to understand what's
happening now one possible resolution to
this Paradox is that the the idea of a
classical white hole is an
oversimplification and maybe in a
quantum theory of gravity whenever we
have that white hole may not be a well
well defined it may not have a well
defined event horizon or Singularity or
it may actually be a more complex
Quantum gravitational object with
different properties from what we expect
from classical general relativity that's
a possibility and it could also be
possible that white holes are actually
the end of wormholes or something like
that and maybe whatever is is coming in
through one throat of the through one
mouth of the wor worm Wormhole is
actually being emitted from the other
end which could be white hole that is a
possibility that that we can consider so
maybe that could you know uh take care
of
cality um so yeah the point you're
making is valid white holes seem to
violate cality but it's probably because
we don't understand physics that well at
in those extreme conditions of extreme
curvature extreme density Etc once we
understand that we may find that
causality is actually not violated now
what about our universe being uh inside
a white hole so there are theories of
the of maybe that suggest that maybe the
universe we live in is the interior of a
black hole or a white hole so how do we
prove or disprove that there's no way of
doing it and there are certain um
properties of the universe that don't
make sense if we were if it were the
interior of of a white hole or a black
hole for example our universe is
expanding the acceleration the expansion
is accelerating we know that now if you
have a black hole or a white hole does
its Event Horizon
expand only then you you would have the
expansion of space time within it right
so that doesn't fit with the hypothesis
that the universe is is the interior of
of a black hole or white hole and then
you have something called Cosmic
microwave background radiation which is
the leftover Afterglow of the big bang
and we have evidence that that clearly
points to the fact that a big bang
happened so all of that once again does
not fit in with the hypothesis that the
universe is the interior of a white hole
or black hole so there are these
challenges when it comes to these
observational issues right we we have
observational evidence that tell tell
you that it's not the interior of a
white hole or black hole so so most
likely the answer is no to
that okay Asha kashia says I am in Okay
Asha Kash I am in grade e awesome I am
interested in astrophysics and
cosmology please suggest some things
that I should do I should start in order
to have a strong foundation in these
topics well I really I'm really glad
that you are interested in astrophysics
and cosmology grade eight that's
wonderful I'm glad to see more kids
taking an interest in these matters so
if you want to have a strong foundation
in astrophysics and
cosmology uh you first of all if you
want to have a career in this and you're
serious about that then you're going to
have to strengthen your mathematics and
science skills so when it comes to
mathematics you need to focus on
mastering the subjects like algebra and
geometry which are essential for
understanding higher level physics
Concepts and you need to start learning
trigonometry and calculus these are all
fun topics you know the thing is this
you've heard of the Trojan Horse story
right Trojan Horse the Greek the Greeks
left this trojan horse at the walls of
Troy and then they left and the the
Trojans brought the horse inside they
thought it's a great gift from Greece
and inside the Trojan Horse Were
Soldiers so physics is like that physics
is a nice trojan horse that looks pretty
and you want to play with it but inside
physics is
mathematics so if you are really serious
about learning about having a career in
physics or or doing physics seriously
you're going to have to learn
mathematics and math can be really great
fun if you learn it properly from the
fundamentals up upwards so you're going
to have if you if you want to have a
strong Foundation you're going to have
to learn uh algebra geometry
trigonometry calculus and then you need
to master physics from the ground up so
you need to first begin with the basics
of classical mechanics Newton's Laws of
Motion gravity Etc hel resnic is a great
book for that I think one of the
editions is over here that's a great
book it's fun to study okay so
understanding these fundamental
principles the classical mechanics
Newton's Laws Etc gravitation all of
that is is essential for it's crucial
for studying astrophysics and then you
will need to know some chemistry some
biology because these Sciences
interesting
with astrophysics in in the sense of
astrochemistry astrobiology but mainly
it's physics and Mathematics and then
you will need to read some books you can
start with popular books what Neil
degrass Tyson has good books uh there is
Cosmos by Carl
Sean Stephen Hawking Brief History of
Time Etc there are lots of educational
resources available online NASA has has
good resources I believe Khan Academy
has good resources you know good videos
and all that uh so that would
uh maybe help you build better
fundamentals but the best way to learn
something is through a textbook get
yourself a good textbook so since you're
in grade 8th just focus on the on the
fundamentals basics of Mathematics
Algebra trigonometry calculus geometry
and basics of physics which is Newtonian
physics gravity all that eventually
you're going to have to learn quantum
mechanics thermodynamics and all that it
it it's it's a long process it's not
something you will do overnight and you
can keep in touch with what's happening
what what's the news in physics right
now you can watch videos you can watch
pod listen to podcasts you can uh do all
that there are online communities and
forums that you can join and so on so
forth you can perhaps even start a blog
or a vlog or or work on some project you
know acquire telescope learn how to
operate that learn what's Parallax and
stuff like that so these are the things
you could do but to genuinely develop a
strong Foundation you need the the basic
math skills and the in the proper
foundation in basic physics Newtonian
physics that's what you can do and it's
a process it's not something you'll be
able to do in a couple of weeks it'll
it's I think if you start now in a year
or two you'll have a reasonably good
foundation and uh then by the time
you're in college you could be very
strong you could have a strong
foundation in these fields in these
subjects so all the
best okay prna Nala says how is the
lo How can the location of nuclear
physics not be tracked how why is it so
difficult to track the location of of
nuclear submarines and what makes
nuclear submarines
special nuclear submarines are these
undersea
underwater warship shs
right so they are highly sophisticated
they're they're extremely expensive very
uh prized strategic effect
uh Assets in in in Naval Warfare they
have strength they have endurance they
have power endurance as in how long can
you go can you BC without being
replenished and so on and their ability
to remain undetected is is is the most
important factor in their effectiveness
so what is it so let's say I want to
track a nuclear submarine what do I need
to do first of all I would need to I can
use equipment that can listen for sound
nonnatural sound in the oceans right so
if you listen to an ocean to the ocean
you will find all kinds of natural
sounds you know the sounds of the Waves
up there at the surface of the ocean
then you have all kinds of marine life
you have Dolphins you've got whales
whales whales songs are Extremely Loud
and they go on for thousands of
kilometers they can they can travel for
thousands of kilometers and so on so
there are all kinds of natural sounds
but you're listening for unnatural
sounds right so when it comes to nuclear
submarines they are designed to minimize
noise there are various materials sound
damping materials and such structures
that are that are uh used in nuclear
submarines to reduce What's called the
acoustic signature or or the amount of
sound that they emit then they will have
very quiet propulsion systems okay so
typically in a submarine standard
oldfashioned submarine you have
propellers propellers and these
propellers they make a lot of lot of
noise if you're going at a high speed
you going to have cavitation and it's
going to make a lot of noise but in a
nuclear submarine you would typically
have something called a pump jet system
pump jet system which is way quieter
than traditional propellers and the
nuclear reactor itself is much much much
quieter than compared to diesel engines
because you don't need combustion you
don't have air intake and exhaust and
all that so nuclear subes are way
quieter nuclear reactors are way quieter
then the the the hull the external part
of the submarine the hull it has
generally a very streamlined shape shape
like a shark or something to reduce drag
to reduce hydrodynamic noise and to make
it harder to detect by sonar then you
have a
coating which is designed to reduce
Echoes it it absorbs sonar wav and
reduces the strength of the echo that
returns to the sonar
operator and so on so forth then nuclear
submarines can go to significant depths
the deeper you go the harder you are to
detect the faster you go the the harder
you are to detect and it obviously runs
silently and the nuclear reactor itself
it gives you essentially almost
unlimited range the range of a nuclear
submarine is limited only by the amount
of food and water Etc that it can store
on board and the number of personnel the
the the size of the crew let's say you
got 50 people and each person needs to
eat a certain amount of food and drink a
certain amount of water per day then if
so multiply that by 50 multiply that by
let's say whatever number of days and
you can store that much food in the
submarine so there are submarines
nuclear submarines that can go that can
stay submerged for six months at a time
or maybe even longer so they can have
extended missions they don't need
refueling they don't need to go up for
air you can recycle the air also scrub
the air carbon dioxide and keep on
recycling it and so on so there are lots
of uh factors okay the nuclear reactor
provides a lot of power propulsion it
has a high speed and so on so forth and
so these are the factors that make
nucleus submarines uh so hard to detect
and because they remain submerged for
such a long time you essentially have
almost no way of knowing where a nuclear
submarine could be lurking so these are
some of the things that make them
special okay I think uh we've done a lot
of questions let's take one question
about AI it's by asak kup what's the
future of AI how can we use AI to our
advantage and what are all the career
options one could explore within it look
the future of AI is kind of scary
H uh we have uh AI systems I mean the AI
systems that are visible to the public
are your standard chat Bots which is
chat GPT 3.5 and they have 4.0 also then
you have clothe you have Bard Etc these
are chat bots so you can ask questions
and it it answers you back in in human
like text
okay so that's what you have and it can
give you answers about essentially
anything if you have if you're a
business person if you give it what your
business is like and the specifics of
your business it can actually give you
strategies about how you can you know
have more sales or more growth or
whatever uh and and so so much more and
you can automate lots of tasks and all
that so AI is
becoming exponentially more
sophisticated and more powerful almost
every week almost every month and what
we are seeing is just the tip of the
iceberg and AI systems can be used to
optimize themselves so that makes the
Improvement the speed of Improvement
almost exponential the only limitation
is how much computing power and and
energy you can throw at the AI system so
it is entirely possible that in the next
two three years AI systems could become
super intelligent I'm not sure if they
will
become self-aware that's not actually
the issue the issue is that they're
going to become so so intelligent
they're going to far exceed human
intelligence they just algorithms they
just computation
machines prediction machines but they're
going to become so incredibly powerful
that the human mind is going to be
almost nothing compared to it in the
next two three years that's going to
have all kinds of
applications in um the military domain
and uh other domains so essentially what
that means is that
most of the power in the world will be
concentrated in the hands of one or two
Nations and the Nations that are not
developing AI systems are going to be
left way way way behind down back in the
road side that's what to happen and
obviously what's the future of a there's
going to be more Automation in
Industries there's going to be
uh much more enhanced decision decision
making Predictive Analytics is very
important business it's also important
in war gaming in military applications
real-time data processing uh stock
market and whatnot Healthcare Finance
all that stuff it's going to give you
lots of wonderful personalized
experiences So you you're going to have
movies tailored to your tastes and all
that music tailored to your tastes
Health Care education
entertainment personalized learning
plans personalized customized Medical
Treatments tailored specifically
tailored content and so on and uh
there's going to be all that so yeah
there's going to be tremendous
tremendous changes in the world in the
next two to three years okay it's going
to totally I mean we're going to have a
post pre 23 and pre 2023 and post 2023
World essentially when did the AI first
came come out 23 22 somewhere around
that time uh so that's what it's going
to do how can we use AI to our advantage
uh you can improve effic efficiency you
can use AI to automate repetitive tasks
mundane tasks so you can focus on more
complex and more creative stuff right um
it can enhance creativity you can use AI
as a personal research assistant U you
can ask AI to generate lots of new ideas
you can even have ai create artwork for
you you can have ai create music for you
uh you can have ai design various
iterations of products for you so you
can use AI to to uh enhance your
creativity and explore all kinds of new
possibilities then obviously a can give
you insights about insights and
recommendations based on lots of data
and and things like that so if you are
if you are into a business if you are a
business owner you can use that to your
advantage so you can make decisions that
are better informed and that can give
you an advantage over your competitors
if you are a student you can use AI to
learn stuff you can you know I mean most
teachers especially in certain countries
are terrible it's very hard to to
understand to learn complex subjects but
AI can make that really easy and if Ai
and you can use AI tailored to your your
learning aptitude and your learning
processes to really fast track skill
acquirement and acquisition you know it
will you can tailor it to your learning
style and you can continuously keep
learning stuff based on that then
obviously
AI it can help doctors diagn NOS
diseases based on you know pattern
recognition you can have apps you know
variable devices and apps that can give
you real time insights into your overall
health what's your blood pressure what's
your uh what's your heart rate and
various other parameters I'm sure that
can be monitored and tracked in real
time it can give you entire charts and
data and it can give you uh you know
recommendations and give you warnings in
advance if it can identify patterns that
could lead to which could indicate
certain diseases and all that so so so
you can do all these things with AI know
that's how you can leverage Ai and uh
help it
give help you give have a better life so
that's how we can use AI to your
advantage what are the carer
options uh data scientist is one okay uh
you analyze and interpret complex data
to help your organization make better
decisions
you used machine learning and various
statistical techniques and algorithms to
extract insights from the data and give
actionable outputs and all that so there
is data scientist then there is machine
learning machine learning engineer so in
that you will Design and develop machine
learning algorithms and models they're
going to work on implementation and
testing and deployment of various AI
systems in various applications so that
is machine learning engineer then you
have ai research scientist there is AI
ethics which is a field which will which
will emerge you know developing
guidelines and policies to ensure that
your AI system is reasonable it is
responsible it doesn't do something
nasty whatever then robotics robotics
engineering merged with AI in
conjunction with AI so you can design
and build robots that can perform a
variety of tasks and you integrate robot
AI with these robots so these low robots
will be able to perceive and learn and
interact with their environment and get
better and better over time reasonably
rapidly um so cyber security there
there's going to be applications of AI
and you can obviously teach AI so AI
educator AI trainer so you're going to
create curriculum curriculums and teach
courses on AI and machine learning so
that will help prepare the next
generation of AI professionals that's
the kind of future jobs that you can
have future carer options that involve
artificial intelligence that's what I
can say okay let's take some questions
from the live chat
now
okay Rohit jangid says can we replicate
the cognitive abilities of the human
brain through artificial intelligence
because our decisions are bed are based
on previous knowledge and experiences
and the same can be with AI models
yes so AI models are based on the neural
net Network thing right neural network
so they kind of
replicate the structure of the neurons
and the way neurons interact with each
other and that's how AI has been built
its neural
networks so yes eventually a large
enough AI will kind of possibly
replicate the cognitive abilities of the
human brain in the next two three years
you will have super intelligent AIS
which will be which will be able to
process which essentially will dwarf the
human brain the human in in terms of
whatever the human intellect can do so
AI is already reaching that stage AI
systems chat Bots can
essentially pass the student test you
cannot tell whether that system is human
or not that's how good they are they can
talk just like a human being a very
intelligent human being so yes our
decisions are based on previous
knowledge and previous experiences and
through machine learning and through all
these techn through all these techniques
the same thing happens with AI so these
AI systems are trained on tremendously
large data sets so they also acquire
previous knowledge and experience and
that's how they're able to behave the
way they do so yes we have already kind
of replicated the uh some aspects of the
functioning of the human brain cognitive
abilities so for cognition you need
senses we have five senses you know
sense taste smell sound and sight five
senses when it comes to AI they don't
have these five senses is they only have
the data that we provide them as as a
training for training we train AI
reinforcement learning and whatever
other part ways of doing it so AI only
can sense that data and it can sense
your inputs when you're talking to Ai
and then it can give you a you know
answers so it doesn't it it lacks the
sensory abilities of human beings if we
were to give those sensory abilities to
AI then it could take a whole different
dimension so you can't replicate
everything of the human brain because
the human brain is equipped with all
these sense organs and it is sensing all
this the external environment in real
time it is gathering inputs data in real
time and we don't even realize we're
doing that that is something AI
lacks but if we were to give that
ability to to AI then it could behave
just like a human brain brain
possibly
okay um dures says will time travel be
possible in the future if so why aren't
we seeing any time travelers in the
present and what is more harder what is
harder traveling to the future or
traveling to the past we don't know see
you're absolutely right if TR time
travel were to be were possible then we
would be seeing Time Travelers today who
have come from the future and we haven't
seen any of those there have been some
cases of some people who have claimed
that they have come from the future but
how do you prove
that so uh so you're right if time
travel were possible we would actually
meet people from the future who have
traveled to our present point in time
and we don't do that and we don't meet
any such people or maybe if it is true
if if they are traveling maybe they are
very well disguised I don't know okay
uh so time travel physics wise um there
are certain solutions to Einstein's
field equations uh that kind of allow
time travel wormholes wormholes are
shortcuts between two particular two two
different locations in
SpaceTime and if you have two ends of a
wormhole and one of the ends you make it
you you move it at relativistic speeds
then time dilation ET all those effects
will come together to produce what looks
like time travel so yes theoretically
time travel is possible but there are
problems with wormholes how to keep a
wormhole throat open and so on so forth
I've spoken about that in the past so uh
technologically we don't have the
technology to make that happen we don't
even know if wormholes exist we've never
observed a wormhole and so on so it may
be possible theoretically for a super
intelligent species maybe we are just
too too too primitive and too
unintelligent to make that happen so
maybe that's why we don't see time
travels because maybe in the future the
human species never reaches that level
of intelligence and that level of
technological press where it can make
this happen maybe aliens can travel
through time a high super intelligent
species if they exist in other parts of
the universe possibly what's harder
traveling to the future of the past it's
all speculative we don't really
know uh
okay uh let us see some more science
questions as always we get questions
about things other than science but let
me try and find some science related
questions mang says is it safe for
us to give AI the access to the buttons
for nuclear weapons or any weapon that
is the scariest scenario that you can
imagine giving AI access to weapons and
the worst weapon is the nuclear weapon
right nuclear weapons so we have those
robots right those robot dogs let me put
that on the screen robot
dogs where do you have it
so the these things these robot dogs
what if you take this robot dog and you
put a there you have it a machine gun on
it and then you allow it to operate the
Machine Gun auto autonomously based on
its own intelligence AI so then you have
a killing machine right robot dogs with
with with machine guns there you have it
flamethrowers machine guns and then you
unleash a hoorde you know a thousand of
these on the battlefield what what you
going to do it's a nightmare scenario
look at this excuse
me so we are already at this at this
level at the stage of of development of
Robotics and Ai and I believe the
Chinese are trying this off yeah China
shows off robot dogs armed with machine
guns so we are already there it is not
safe at all it is the scarest thought
you can
imagine I mean the military will do this
militaries across the world will start
adopting this those who have the
capability to do that but imagine giving
that to police
forces that will be out there in the Civ
civilian domain essentially uh so some
countries may do that which is a really
scary thought so yeah and then the
decision making of whether to take a
human life or not is entirely
algorithmic there is no ethics or
morality behind that that is scary it's
it's the Terminator scenario right
Terminator and then imagine giving AI
systems access to nuclear launch
capabilities so the AI will decide
whether you launch a ballistic missile
with let's say 10 mved Warheads or not I
mean imagine that there's no human inter
intervention in that you should not do
that I don't know if so there are only a
handful of Nations that have nuclear
capabilities and out of those Nations
maybe
two or three of them may have the AI
capabilities
Edge AI capabilities the US and and
China I don't think I don't think Russia
has that I don't think India has that so
um yeah it's it's a scariest scenario
can you can imagine AI systems with
access to nuclear launch
capabilities
um let us look man once again people ask
me about non science topics it it hides
the other questions about science that
uh that people are
asking okay abishek shast says why does
Saturn has a ring system and why are
they all in the same
plane okay let's put Saturn on the
screen what does Saturn look like Saturn
is this planet right very famous Planet
very iconic planet in the solar system
it's a planet with
rings and the Rings are all in the same
plane so the answer to this question is
similar to The question as to why are
all most of the planets in the solar
system in the same plane why are they
not all you know in different planes
they're they're all in the same plane
it's because it all goes back to the
birth of the solar system the solar
system was born out of a protostellar
cloud a cloud of gas and dust mainly
hydrogen gas and dust and other space
debris
that were the result of the violent
death of an older star so an older star
several billion years ago when super NOA
baboom Kaboom exploded spewed out all
its internal contents it became a
gigantic
nebula and over time this again coales
or maybe it was multiple Stars whose
nebulas came together and it all so
maybe we have blood blood and calci ium
and all oxygen nitrogen in our bodies
maybe the calcium in my left hand and
the calcium in my right hand came from
different stars but whatever we are made
of is star material so this protostellar
nebula started coaling because of self
gravitation it started because of self-
gravitation it started rotating
essentially around a center where the
star where the new Star emerged and
everything was rotating around the
center of mass which was this new star
which was the
very the baby son let's say our son so
it was all in the same plane and that's
why all the planets are in the same
plane and Saturn also Saturn rotates
around that plane the axis of Revolution
rotation of Saturn is in the same plane
and it looks like at some point in time
in the history of Saturn one of its
moons or maybe two of its moons collided
and got destroyed and the debris that
came out of this became the rings of
Saturn so that is what would have
happened and obviously the moons were
would also be in in the same plane as
the plane of the solar system or at a
slight inclination perhaps and that's
why they are all in the same
plane Karan nwat says is the earth
conscious well we don't have evidence of
whether it's conscious or
not how do we know I mean when we see
Consciousness we recognize it you see
any animal you know it's conscious you
know it immediately cat dog horse cow
spider whatever mosquito also has a
certain amount of Consciousness whale
conscious so when you see a being with
Consciousness you know it has
Consciousness you recognize it
immediately even plants have a certain
amount of Consciousness they all
perceive the light of the sun and the
warmth of the Sun and sunflowers always
turn their faces towards the sun and
plants perceive when it's darkness when
it's night so the leaves you know kind
of crumple down in the night in the
morning they all come out again so
plants also have some level of primitive
rudimentary Consciousness so when we see
something with Consciousness we
recognize it do rocks have
Consciousness we don't see we don't
think of rocks as being conscious do
mountains of Consciousness well as far
as we know we don't see a mountain as as
something that has Consciousness
similarly does a planet have
Consciousness where
as far as we know it doesn't seem to
have Consciousness that way does a
Galaxy have Consciousness so the main
question is what is consciousness and
that is something we don't have an
answer to so there you have it the
answer is we don't know but most likely
probably
not okay ad takur says what are brains
in cosmology are are the part of the
same universe or connected in some
manner so in brain
cosmology there is something called the
bulk which Which is higher
dimensional
thing okay so we see the world in three
or four dimensions three dimensions of
space and one dimension of time we do
perceive the passage of time yesterday
right now tomorrow time passes it goes
in a certain direction we perceive
vaguely the passage of time and we see
we observe three dimensions of space so
those are the four dimensions we are
familiar with so in super string theory
in M Theory in brain
cosmology uh the actual super
structure of the universe let's say or
what's beyond the universe is higher
dimensional so there are multiple
Dimensions there could be 10 Dimensions
there could be 11 Dimensions there could
be 26 dimensions in bosonic string
string theory
Etc and according to brain Theory brain
world theory M Theory our universe is a
three-dimensional membrane that exists
within a much larger higher dimensional
bulk okay so this membrane that is our
universe exists in in a higher
dimensional maybe 10 dimensional or 11
dimensional uh material called the bulk
and maybe it was the Collision of two
three-dimensional brains that gave rise
to the Big Bang in the universe and
maybe it's a cyclical process it happens
from time to time or it extremely long
periods of
time so yeah that's what brains are in
cosmology they are part of the larger
hyper Universe let's say okay and the
collisions and interactions between
brains maybe they give rise to multiple
universes it's all theoretical we can't
falsify it so maybe it's
philosophical okay let's take maybe a
couple more questions
Gulu says Gulu says why why can't we
create a living cell in a laboratory
despite knowing its composition yeah I
believe I read recently that somebody
had created artificial living cells or
something I'm not sure how far they have
succeeded in that so
yeah if you can create artificial life
you can essentially play God right but I
don't think we are there yet I don't
think we may ever be there we don't know
about that
so once again the question about
Consciousness is like the question about
life what is life when we see something
we know it's alive or not but we can't
Define life there are certain
definitions of life but there are
certain organisms that are on the
dividing line between life and death
viruses a virus has DNA but it doesn't
have equilibrium with with its
environment it doesn't react to external
stimuli a virus it doesn't affect its
external environment like a bacterium
does
but it has DNA and it does replicate so
it has that those characteristics of
life but in from certain perspectives of
viruses are like crystals they are
crystalline structures so virus is on
the dividing line between life and
death so what is life is the question
and we don't quite have the answer from
a physics perspective from a chemistry
perspective from a biology perspective a
clear definition of what is
life and yeah it's this mysterious thing
and uh so we still haven't reached the
the the technological or whatever
capabilities of being able to create
living cells we
can take existing living cells and
modify them we can take an egg cell egg
cell from a sheep remove its nucleus and
then insert genetic material from a
different sheep and clone it and induce
cell division which essentially leads to
cloning so we can take existing living
cells and modify them and and play
around with that but somehow or the
other we are not able to create
artificial living cells from
scratch because we don't quite
understand even now how it works the
cell membranes the the organel within a
cell the golgy bodies the mitochondria
the end endoplasmic retic reticulum and
whatever else is in their plasmids
uh Celia how does all this work we still
don't quite know mitochondria really
interesting these are the energy
generators within cells mitochondria can
have temperatures of about 50 plus
degrees Celsius in human beings which is
what produces our internal heat we don't
know how these things really work it's
extremely complicated the biochemistry
of all this so because we don't
understand this very well we can't
create living cells in Labs even though
we kind of know what the composition is
we have very high level understanding of
the comp composition the chemical
processes the biochemistry in that is
extraordinarily
complicated and yeah we still are far
from understanding all
this
um Sam AA says are feelings just
chemical reactions in our brain if so
then why are the different for for
everyone look I don't know if my
feelings are different from the feelings
of other people I don't know I can only
experience what's in here I can only
assume what happens in the minds of
others other people I assume there are
people around me I assume this world
exists
but can I be sure maybe it's all a
figment of my imagination who knows who
knows for sure this this is called
solipsism okay it's a philosophical uh
path of thinking you could say
philosophical school of thought
solipsism maybe the only thing that
exists in the in the universe is you
your mind
and everything you apparently perceive
and imagine is all the creation of your
imagination it's possible now so that's
solipsism that's a solipsistic line of
philosophical thinking but feelings we
have feelings you mean I think you mean
emotions right happiness sadness Joy
misery depression whatever else exists
feeling blue feeling green whatever
right so these are
emotions and we have feelings like we
feel stuff right you do that you feel
some some um sensation that's also
feeling let's say so they are these
Sensations they travel through our
nerves all the way into spinal column
and into our brain and then we then it
registers in our brain as a
sensation is this all chemistry is it
all chemical reactions well you actually
have electrical impulses also in the
nerves which travel through chemical
pathways sodium iron chain and whatnot I
remember studying some of that at some
point in time so I don't know if
feelings are different for for everyone
I don't know if emotions are different
for everyone some people are more prone
to being joyous and happy some people
have a very positive optimistic outlook
on life some people are they feel blue
all the time some people are prone to
various some people are prone to
depression for example and so on uh and
and in the US in the Western World they
typically try to alter your State of
Mind by preserving by by prescribing
various chemical
substances some people do
self-medication through alcohol through
through drugs which changes your state
of mind then you have certain
anti-depressants like what Prozac or
what not which kind of messes with your
neurochemistry so does it mean it's all
chemical reactions to some extent maybe
but to some extent maybe not we don't
quite know we don't know how the mind
works we don't know how the brain works
Psychiatry is is wodoo it's all hand
waving
okay it the the the organ that
Psychiatry is supposed to
study do we do psychiatrist ever image
image the organ do they ever map the
organ for example if you have a fracture
you're going to have an x-ray
right so your your orthopedic surgeon or
doctor is going to x-ray your your arm
if your arm is fractured so you're going
to see exactly what is wrong with it and
then you're going to fix it let's say
you have some problem and you need a CD
scan or you need a sonography or
whatever so whatever organ is affected
you're going to image that organ you
going to you're going to you're going to
map it properly and then you're going to
pinpoint what the problem is and then
you fix it when it comes to Psychiatry
do they actually see what's going on in
the brain what regions of the BL brain
are lit up through through brain waves
or whatever when you're thinking when
you're depressed what you
whatever that's not done so we so it's
because we don't understand the brain at
all so I would say that to claim that
feelings are chemical reactions emotions
are chemical reactions is is
oversimplifying things there are many
scientists who do that very intelligent
scientists I know some of them feelings
are chemical reactions thoughts are
chemical reactions everything is
chemistry how do you know that how do
you prove that so I
think I think the brain I think the Mind
Etc is way more complex than this and
it's just oversimplification
um Rohan says what is repulsive gravity
sounds like something that would be the
cause of the universe's expansion
well the cause of the universe's
expansion is this apparent energy that
in that is inherent to SpaceTime itself
and we call it dark energy for for lack
of a better term we don't know what it
is we don't know if it's a fifth Force
we don't know if it's a repulsive form
of gravity we don't know if it's some
fluid that imbus space we don't know
what it is we actually have some
understanding of what Dark Matter could
be maybe it's a family of particles
maybe it's a class of particles maybe
primordial black holes of something
something to do with it some would say
that maybe neutros are a component of
dark matter because they interact only
through the weak force and so on and so
forth we have some understanding of of
Dark Matter maybe it's
just
m uh modified neonian Dynamics maybe
that you know explains what dark matter
is but the expansion of the universe the
accelerating expansion of the universe
we don't know how to explain that and we
we call that dark energy we don't know
what it is it looks like it's something
that is a repulsive form of gravity
perhaps but it's it's causing the
expansion of SpaceTime itself so we are
nowhere close to even beginning to
understand or speculate as to what it
could be maybe it's quintessence maybe
it's something else yeah but as far as
you know there is no repulsive gravity
we have never observed repulsive gravity
we have never measured repulsive gravity
we have never observed a phenomenon in
which instead of falling down a particle
or an object falls upwards which would
be repulsive
gravity how would repulsive gravity work
well to over simp to hyper oversimplify
it take the neonian potential and where
you have M replace M with minus M and
then you have repulsive gravity if you
have a negative Mass it's going to be
repulsive but we have never observed
negative Mass could negative Mass exist
well according to the equations you just
put replace M with minus M and then
everything works the other way so that
could be repulsive gravity so if
negative Mass exists you would have
repulsive gravity right away but we have
never observed that so there you have
it uh om B says is it possible that the
sun Sun's previous generation Star had
habitable planets it's possible
certainly possible so we have so many
space rocks that we have inherited some
of those space rocks the asteroid some
of them could have possibly come from
the previous generation star from the
death and destruction of the previous
generation star um so yes to answer your
question in short it's entirely possible
that the previous generation the the the
star that was the previous incarnation
of of of the sun could have had planets
possibly even habitable planets but how
do we know for sure we
can't
okay Ral says does the Multiverse
actually exist do we have any evidence
we have zero evidence why do we have
zero evidence because we can't even
observe our own Universe in its entirety
we can only observe a small part of the
universe which is about roughly 90
billion light years in diameter that's
it the actual universe is way way larger
than that but we can't observe it
because the universe is expanding and
Beyond the observable Horizon the
universe is is expanding super luminally
faster than the speed of light SpaceTime
is expanding faster than the speed of
light which is allowed by the laws of
physics so that's why uh we can't
observe what's beyond the obser what's
beyond the cosmic Horizon the observable
Horizon and that's just our universe so
how do we know what's beyond our
universe
we can't right so we don't know if a
multivers exists U according to certain
theories of physics Multiverse could
exist there is the string theory
landscape in which there could be five
10 rais 10 rais to 500 different
possible universes with different
physical properties then you have uh the
many worlds interpretation of quantum
mechanics which also could lead to a
Multiverse yeah it could be so but we
have no evidence it actually uh
exists no observational
evidence okay let's maybe take one more
question one more
question okay I okay what happened
before the Big Bang we don't know we
don't have any data from before the Big
Bang whatever data we have have in
existence is what we can see in the
universe Cosmic microwave background
radiation all the stars planet planet
planets galaxies and light light is cmbr
Cosmic microwave background radiation
all of that based on that we have made
formulated our best theory our best
model our best chronology of the
evolution of the universe which is
called The Big Bang Theory and the model
that describes everything that we have
in existence is called the Lambda CDM
model the Lambda cold Dark Matter model
standard cosmological model none of that
tells us what happened before the Big
Bang and if you were to go into that you
would go enter the realm of speculation
and hypothesis not Theory so one of the
hypothesis is the brain World cosmology
M Theory in which maybe the universe was
created by the Collision of two
three-dimensional brains in a higher
dimensional bulk and the Collision of
the two brains G released the tremendous
amounts of energy that led to the Big
Bang that's a possibility that's a
hypothesis but there is no way to prove
or disprove it it is non
falsifiable all right all
right uh so that's what could perhaps
have happened before the Big Bang but we
cannot know for
sure and I think I'm going to end this
session with that question I know there
are lots and lots of other questions um
okay let's take one last question by
gorov what will happen if the
International Space Station will no
longer be operational why are there no
photos or videos from the Chinese space
station are they experimenting on
another virus look I don't know I don't
know what they're doing on their space
station they have released some
photographs of their space walks Etc the
Chinese um so yeah there are a few
photos available maybe a couple of
videos from the Chinese space station
but we don't know what they are doing in
space obviously it's all classified they
will release some information but most
of it will be classified and not
released to the public may maybe they're
experimenting on something or the other
we can't speculate I I have not been
there so I don't know what they're doing
so I can't say whether they're
experimenting on a virus or a plant or
whatever it is what will happen when the
if ISS is no longer operational
eventually look you can always keep on
replacing this the parts of the
International Space Station repairing
stuff bringing more supplies bringing
more parts you know and you can always
keep on uh keeping it operational but
eventually in the future if it is no
longer operational then its orbit will
Decay and it will
eventually so once it is no longer
operational they will no longer keep on
doing the orbit raising Maneuvers with
rockets with boosters or whatever prop
and so its orbit will naturally Decay
and eventually it will re-enter the
atmosphere of the earth
and burn up in the atmosphere so that
happened with the me space station in I
don't know when when Meir died was it in
the 1990s early 2000s I don't remember
but the me space station the Russian
space station was eventually deor
and it burned up in the atmosphere
before that the Americans had had
something called Skylab in the 20th
century so that space station also
eventually was deorbited and it burned
up in the atmosphere and eventually the
same thing will happen to the
International Space Station all right
and with that we're going to end this
session thank you so much for all your
questions apologies to those of you
whose questions I could not take but
we're going to keep on doing this
science science physics astrophysics
live streams and I'm going to take all
the possible questions I can so thank
you so much for your participation for
all your questions for your viewership I
really appreciate that and I will see
you in the next live stream which will
be very soon all right until then take
care thank you very much and as always
keep raising your standards keep
learning keep growing thank you bye